<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Simon Crewe</title>
    <link>http://simoncrewe.co.uk/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Simon Crewe</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2017 14:29:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://simoncrewe.co.uk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>My New Post</title>
      <link>http://simoncrewe.co.uk/post/my-new-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2017 14:29:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://simoncrewe.co.uk/post/my-new-post/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;this-is-a-new-post&#34;&gt;This is a new post&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is some content&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Services</title>
      <link>http://simoncrewe.co.uk/page/services/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2017 14:22:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://simoncrewe.co.uk/page/services/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bite Mark Analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Age Estimation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disaster Victim Identification&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expert Identification for the Courts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bite-mark-analysis&#34;&gt;Bite Mark Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assailants occasionally leave tooth marks on their victims’ bodies. Unlike a bruise or ‘black eye’, there may be characteristics in the mark which can identify the assailant. There may be characteristics which can exclude other suspects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These marks change with time, and since especially in live victims, the first person to suspect a bite mark is never the odontologist, it is important to obtain a good undistorted photograph, with a scale clearly shown in the plane of the mark, as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, the odontologist can take impressions of a suspect’s teeth, and compare measured photographs of the casts with the photographs of the injury. An opinion can then be given as to whether the suspect is excluded or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;age-estimation&#34;&gt;Age estimation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The development of the teeth follows a fairly regular timetable, and by examining the dental development of an individual, a fairly accurate estimation of age can be given, up to about twenty-one years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has become useful in determining the rights of young asylum seekers, who arrive with no documentation, but the knowledge that the younger they appear to be, the ‘better’ their entitlement appears to be. Further controversy has entered the situation, in that an x-ray has to be taken for this to be at all accurate, and issues of consent, and clinical need have muddied the waters somewhat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the age of twenty-one, it becomes much more difficult to assess the age from the dentition, because it becomes a matter of assessing the wear on the tooth surfaces, and for this, an idea of the culture in which the person lived is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;disaster-victim-identification&#34;&gt;Disaster Victim Identification&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a motorcycle crashes into a tree, and explodes, leaving two bodies with no paperwork, the police will discover that the owner and her girlfriend are missing. The dental records of the two will be sought, and the two bodies identified. If the records are inadequate, they only need to distinguish between the two bodies to establish which is which.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a commercial airliner crashes into a hotel, the situation is a little more complicated. The aeroplane is technically ‘closed’, so the people aboard are known, but it cannot be certain who was in the hotel at the time. In this situation, a higher level of proof of identity will be required, and visual identification may not be acceptable on its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of dental identification is much the same as in individual cases, except that dental evidence is also used to exclude possible ‘matches’ reducing the odds for other agencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dental evidence played a significant part in the identification of victims from the &lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt; London Bombings, the South East Asian Tsunami, the Concorde crash in Paris, the Mont Blanc Tunnel fire, the Zeebrugge Ferry disaster, and many other disasters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;expert-identification-for-the-courts&#34;&gt;Expert Identification for the Courts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Identification of the dead is not usually a problem. People are usually identified by relatives, or documents such as passports, or identity devices such as military ‘dog tags’, or hospital ID bracelets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the death triggers an inquest, one of the Coroner’s duties is to determine identity beyond reasonable doubt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the face has become too disfigured to compare with photographs, or to show to relatives, reasonable doubt as to the identity may exist, and the value of identity documents may be questioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to the impression given by the media, the next step is not ‘facial reconstruction’, or ‘DNA’, but to get a Forensic Odontologist’s opinion. If dental records are available for the ‘missing person’, they can be compared with the dental features of the unidentified body, and the Odontologist’s opinion given as to whether the identity is confirmed ‘beyond reasonable doubt’, or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the dental evidence is flawed - most usually by inadequate dental records of the missing person, other forms of establishing identity may be ‘added’ to reduce doubt. Digital photographs of the missing person smiling may be overlaid onto images of the teeth of the body, and if there are suitable characteristics that coincide, this evidence can be added to other evidence to establish identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidence offered by the Forensic Pathologist can add weight to an identification - scars, piercings, tattoos, the presence or absence of organs (like the appendix, which may have been surgically removed in life), or of implanted surgical devices. These features may not be unique - except that surgical devices (even dentures) often have a serial number, which can be conclusive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clothing and possessions are also used to add weight to the evidence, if it can be proved that the missing person was wearing a particularly unique item at the time of death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DNA processing at present takes a little more time than it appears to on the television, is not always conclusive, and is more expensive. This situation will certainly improve in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title> The case of the faked bite mark</title>
      <link>http://simoncrewe.co.uk/post/the-case-of-the-faked-bite-mark/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2017 14:20:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://simoncrewe.co.uk/post/the-case-of-the-faked-bite-mark/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is not unknown for faked bite marks to reach court. A fictional example in the recent Wallace and Gromit film, A Matter of Loaf and Death, occurs when the Bake O Lite girl bites herself on the forearm, and has Gromit imprisoned for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gromit’s defence should have been able to show that the mark, although definitely caused by teeth, was not a dog bite and was in a position where it could have been self inflicted. It should not have been necessary to construct casts of Gromit’s own teeth (for comparison with a measured, distortion-free photograph of the mark), but it could be done to show that the mark could not have been made with Gromit’s teeth – except that Gromit doesn’t actually have a mouth!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be expected that the Bake O Lite girl would refuse consent for dental impressions of her teeth; and since Wallace was the only other person present, dental casts of his teeth should have been able to eliminate him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the example is fiction, and comedy at that, such events certainly occur in real life!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title> St John&#39;s Lake </title>
      <link>http://simoncrewe.co.uk/post/st-john-s-lake/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2017 14:17:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://simoncrewe.co.uk/post/st-john-s-lake/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The story goes that one Sunday morning in the 1980s an embarrassed fisherman walked into Torpoint Police Station with a bulging Tesco carrier bag. In it was a mud-encrusted human skull, which he had found while digging for bait in St John’s lake. Overlooking the fact that such digging is forbidden, a discussion took place as to whether the exhibit should be treated as lost property or evidence of a murder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cleaned up skull ended up in our department. The Coroner’s Office needed to know whether the skull was from a recently deceased person, or possibly from a member of the crew of an RFA Coal Carrier which had sunk during the 1940s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://simoncrewe.co.uk/uploads/2017/03/04/0p317.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The skull is dolichocephalic, with a nasal lip, suggesting Caucasian origin. This shape can also be of Negro anthropology, but we were unable to determine this, as it requires comparison with tables to which we had no access. Eyebrow ridges, mastoid process, and masseter attachment indicate that the individual was male.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The teeth were mostly in good condition, except for the upper left first molar which was decayed. The lower third molar teeth were fully erupted, and their root formation appeared to be complete (by radiographic examination), suggesting the individual was at least 20 years old. There was significant wear on the surfaces of all the teeth, including the third molars, which suggests several more years of age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a great deal of hard calculus deposited on the inner surfaces of the teeth on the left side only. This is probably because the man had been chewing only on the other side for some considerable time, one assumes because of the pain from the decayed tooth on the upper left. This tooth had been abscessed for some considerable time, with the abscess cavity displacing the sinus cavity above, and expanding the lateral bony wall until it (presumably) discharged out on to the surface of the cheek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the man had a tooth that was so painful he couldn’t eat properly, and a very visible swollen pustule on his cheek, for some considerable time. The very simplest of dental treatment - an extraction - would have solved his problem, but this was not done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had he been a member of the RFA in the 1940s he would have been unlikely to be allowed to let the tooth get into that state. If it had been like that on his joining, it would have been extracted forthwith. If he had been living on the average diet of the 1930s, he would probably have had more decay, which would have been treated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Determining the age of a person from the wear on their teeth is a very risky business, because it is very dependent on diet. Modern ‘western’ individuals can reach old age with no perceptible wear on their teeth. Rural Asian, or African people often show wear quite early in life, while their urban counterparts do not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more reliable measurement is to determine the amount of pulp regression that has taken place, as there has been a little research correlating age with this recession. It occurs to me that I should try this some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the 1980s, we decided that the wear was pretty severe for the age, and may have meant that the man had lived in the era of stone ground flour - before about 1820. This would also account for his lack of dentistry. Or would it? Even before 1820, there were people that could take a tooth out. Our man would have to be very poor, or extremely unfortunate, to be unable to get some help. And how did he end up in St Johns Lake?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we resorted very quickly to to conjecture, imagination and faulty research. Between about 1790 and 1812, civilian prisoners and prisoners of war were held in hulks like these, moored in the Hamoaze. One of our less reliable informants told us that St Johns Lake was the site of one of these hulks, and burials from this vessel accounted for the area being known as Dead Man’s Lake, for the frequency of cannon balls being found there, and for the ban on digging bait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://simoncrewe.co.uk/uploads/2017/03/04/0p316.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really interesting, but so far I have learned that Dead Man’s Bay is on the other side of the Tamar, that no hulk was moored anywhere in St John’s Lake, bait digging is controlled, not forbidden, since the area is a SSSI, and the cannonballs are remains from gun exercise. Since HMS Raleigh overlooks the area, it was suggested that this was the source of the gunfire. But the kind of balls that are found in the lake predate HMS Raleigh, which was only started in the 1940s. It seems more likely that the guns were fired into the bay from a vessel moored outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are many other reasons that a body might end up in the Tamar before 1820. But a prisoner of war, held on a hulk near the 18th Century site of the Naval Dockyard is certainly a candidate. He would have no medical attention and if he died aboard, he would probably have been dropped overboard in a shroud weighted with something (but I doubt a cannonball). Even before the shroud and body broke up, the whole thing might have travelled on the tide. The currents in that area are very strong. The bodies of people that do not survive a jump from the Tamar suspension bridge, are often recovered from the strand at Bere Alston, a considerable distance upstream from the bridge. In addition to the fierce currents, in the early 1800s, the boat traffic in that area would have been considerable, and a body going into the water at North Corner soon after high tide, might well snag up in the bay opposite - St John’s lake, as the tide fell.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is a forensic odontologist?</title>
      <link>http://simoncrewe.co.uk/post/what-is-a-forensic-odontologist/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2017 14:14:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://simoncrewe.co.uk/post/what-is-a-forensic-odontologist/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A forensic odontologist is a dentist who specialises in interpreting dental evidence for the courts. In fact, most of the work done by these experts involves the identification of human remains; that is because, in many cases, the dental examination can give an indication of the age of the person at the time of death, which can help to reduce the number of missing persons being considered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, dental records of the missing persons are compared with the dental condition of the body and an identification may be confirmed. The odontologist will prepare a written report for the Coroner, but is rarely called to support it in person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the investigation is one of homicide, the odontologist can give more information about injuries to the head, and also what injuries may have been made by the teeth of an assailant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That expertise can be extended to examination of the living: the victims of assault. The odontologist has now migrated from examining teeth in the mortuary to examining marks on skin in police stations. Perhaps that accounts for the use of the term odontologist rather than dentist. This time the odontologist’s statement is for the court and they may well have to appear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible to build up a picture from the bite mark of the dentition that caused it. That picture may be only partial or unclear, depending on how well the skin has recorded the mark and how well the mark has been recorded for use as evidence. If the victim of the bite is living the photographic record contains the only evidence, but if it does not display it correctly it is not available to the court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two further extensions of the original remit exist: some odontologists are involved in analysis of weapon marks, since the experience of analysing and interpreting the marks made by teeth is exactly applicable to marks made by other instruments. And the ability to estimate age from radiographs of the jaws is used more and more in cases of asylum seekers, whose entitlement to benefits decreases with age and whose documentation may not be all one would wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;identification-problems&#34;&gt;Identification problems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are problems at present with the prosecution of bite mark cases. The first is the relative rarity of forensic odontologists, so that it may not be possible to get an opinion about an injury very quickly. Very often, the first photograph of the mark is taken on a compact digital camera by a po-lice response team and has little evidential value, especially if there is no scale. By the time good photographs are taken the mark may have faded considerably and evidence has been lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is that, although it is sometimes possible to treat a bite mark like a fingerprint and get a positive identification, that is not always the case. So the perception remains that all bite marks are the same and the injury has the same status as a ‘black eye’.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>about</title>
      <link>http://simoncrewe.co.uk/page/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Mar 2017 15:00:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://simoncrewe.co.uk/page/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I got into the subject by being my father’s ‘sidekick’ while I was at school. He was a consultant oral surgeon (nowadays known as maxillofacial surgeons), who was invited to give opinions on the facial injuries sustained by murder victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first case I remember was in the early 1970s in, which a bite mark on the face of the victim had subsequently been divided by a knife-cut. Then, in 1976, a storm at sea delivered (eventually) the bodies of some yachtsmen who were identified by their dental records (transmitted by telex from Switzerland).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also involved us in the controversy about ‘pink post-mortem staining of teeth’. That is a sign that is occasionally taken to indicate a violent cause of death and is also occasionally confused with the signs of carbon monoxide poisoning. So we rubbed shoulders in the literature with the investigators of Reginald Christie at Rillington Place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dentist’s career often involves a few years of working in hospitals around the country as a resident in oral and maxillofacial surgery. I took this a little further by hanging on until I could apply for a post in my father’s own unit back home in Plymouth, where I continued the connection with the forensic practice. Eventually my father retired, but didn’t retire from the forensic practice which he eventually ‘handed over’ on his death in 1999.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then I have worked with the local police homicide teams, the Coroner in cases of identification, local paediatricians and the child abuse investigation units, detective teams investigating rape and increasingly with lawyers defending clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2005 I spent some time in Thailand with the Thai Tsunami Victim Identification Team. I retired from general practice in 2003, but keep my hand in by working as a volunteer with Mercy Ships, doing dental surgery in makeshift facilities in various countries in West Africa. That has developed into my acting as a ‘fixer’ for medical projects in India, and a projected one in Nepal next year.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>